<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An information, concerning the present state of the Jewish nation in Europe and Judea. Wherein the footsteps of Providence preparing a way for their conversion to Christ, and for their deliverance from captivity, are discovered.</title>
            <author>Jessey, Henry, 1603-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03903</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 8336455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J692C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 482.b.3[11]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99889234</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99889234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; B1:3[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An information, concerning the present state of the Jewish nation in Europe and Judea. Wherein the footsteps of Providence preparing a way for their conversion to Christ, and for their deliverance from captivity, are discovered.</title>
                  <author>Jessey, Henry, 1603-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R[obert]. W[hite]. for Thomas Brewster, at the three Bibles near the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Jessey by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from Wing CD-ROM.</note>
                  <note>Appendix, unnumbered pages at end.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing D2863, reel 1258, of the UMI microfilm set "Early English books, 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jews --  Conversion to Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN INFORMATION, CONCERNING The Preſent STATE OF THE <hi>JEWISH NATION</hi> IN <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROPE</hi> and <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DEA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN The footſteps of Providence pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring a way for their Converſion to CHRIST, and for their <hi>Deliverance</hi> from <hi>Captivity,</hi> are diſcovered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Brewſter,</hi> at the three <hi>Bibles</hi> near the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:183677:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183677:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rue-hearted Chriſtian (for we deſire not that this information ſhould come into the hands of any, but of ſuch as thou art) we find it expedient to advertiſe thee of two things before thou enter upon the peruſal of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, thou art intreated to take notice that this diſcourſe is peculiarly intended for ſuch as are ſober-minded, and are acquainted with the Prophecies which concern the Jewiſh Nation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that ſince the printing of this diſcourſe, before it was publiſhed, ſome more diſtinct Informations have been ſent unto us; and becauſe they tend to clear and expreſs more fully ſome matters, which happily would be doubtfully received; therefore we have made an Appendix of them for greater ſatisfaction; and have given them as they were ſent hither in the Authors own words.</p>
            <p>Farewell in the Lord Jeſus, and pray for the Salvation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that it may come out of <hi>Sion</hi> ſhortly; and give the Lord no reſt till he eſtabliſh and till he make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a praiſe in all the earth. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:183677:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183677:3"/>
            <head>An Information, CONCERNING The preſent State of the <hi>Jewiſh Nation</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Iudea.</hi> Wherein the footſteps of Providence preparing a way for their Converſion to Chriſt, and for their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from Captivity, are diſcovered.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch as do believe the Promiſes, that God will be mercifull unto the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he ſtill loveth them for the Fathers ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 11.38 29, 30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>and that his Gifts and Calling to them being without Ripentance he will beſtow mercy upon them through the Mercy whish is ſhewed to us</hi> Gentiles; and ſuch who alſo hope when that Mercy ſhall be ſhewed unto them, whereby all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid,</hi> 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that then their fulneſs and reception into Grace ſhall become to all the world abundant riches, yea as life from the dead: I ſay ſuch as believe and hope for theſe things, ought to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183677:4"/>conſider ſeriouſly what God is now doing towards the effecting of this great work, that is, what preparations are made at this time towards it: and what the way is by which he will bring them and us together, as one flock in one ſheepfold, under Chriſt Jeſus, that we and they by him may glorifie God together. This conſideration is neceſſary to fit us for the work of our Generation, that in our places we may become ſubſervient to his Counſell, and partake of the Comforts which from thence will redound unto his people; for ſuch as mourn for <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and expect that ſhe ſhall be made the glory of the whole earth, <hi>ſhall ſuck and be ſatisfied with the breaſts of her Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and ſhall milk out,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 66.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>and be delighted with the abundance of her Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this effect we ought to obſerve theſe following Informations concerning their preſent State, whereby it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that God doth begin to appear for them by extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Providences, partly in driving them by great afflictions to look up unto him, partly in moving them to conſider the cauſe of thoſe Afflictions to be the ſin of their FORE-FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERS, in neglecting the day of their ſalvation; partly in moving both Chriſtians and Turks to have compaſſion upon them, and by this means opening a dore of hope unto them to find relief; and to us an occaſion to impart through love unto them the myſteries of the Goſpel: for this deſign is upon the heart of many of Gods ſervants, both here and elſewhere, who entertain ſome acquaintance with them, and endeavour to ratifie their Love unto them by works of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to make way for better Communication in due time, whereof the following Informations will give ſome account; that ſuch as are willing to concur with others in Prayers for them, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and in the effects of Charity, to gain them through kindneſs, to have an open ear in due time for us, may not be wanting to the opportunities which God doth offer to help the advancement of his Counſell, which will be a happineſs to all thoſe who are made willing to co-operate therein; and which for their own comfort they are hereby entreated to do.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:183677:4"/>
            <p>Firſt, Then it is to be obſerved that as the diſtreſs of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions doth increaſe in the world, ſo the affliction and miſery of the Jews; They being ſcatered among theſe Nations: muſt alſo needs be encreaſed; for they having no poſſeſſions which they are permitted or willing to own as their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among the Nations, and not being able to return to the Inheritance which they expect as a Nation in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.15.15.18.19, 20, 21, 26, 4. Deut 1.8, 34, 1.2, 3, 4. Dan. 12.1.</note> there the land being theirs by Gods Promiſe, their Affliction and Calamity muſt needs be by ſo much greater then that of other Nations, by how much they are more unſetled then they: For when the Nations with whom they live, are ſo unſetled, that they can neither abide among them, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to any other abode, this muſt needs be to them that time of trouble whereof <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks, which is ſaid to be ſuch <hi>as never was ſince there was a Nation, even to this ſame time;</hi> and becauſe it is promiſed, that when their trouble ſhall come to this height, that then <hi>Michael the great Prince ſhall ſtand up for them:</hi> therefore we muſt conceive, that the time of their deliverance doth draw near: and the greater the diſtreſs and trouble of the Nations will be, the nearer will be their deliverance at hand: For Chriſt tells us, <hi>That Jeruſalem muſt be troden down of the Gentiles, till the times of the Gentiles be fulfilled.</hi> Now the times of the Gentiles are to be fulfilled, <hi>when after the ſigns in the Sun, Moon and Stars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 21.25, 26.</note> whereof many have been already, <hi>there ſhall be ſuch diſtreſs of Nations with ſuch perplexity, as the ſea and for the looking after thoſe things which are coming upon the earth, becauſe the powers of heaven ſhall be ſhaken.</hi> Which things we conceive are now actually begun; and when they end, the times of the Gentiles will be fulfilled, and then the <hi>Shulamite will return.</hi> This diſtreſs of the Nations is now begun in <hi>Europe,</hi> but is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to end in <hi>Aſia</hi> and in <hi>Africa,</hi> and ſhall be ſulfilled when the Propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſhall come to paſs, mentioned, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.23, 24, 25. to the end.<note place="margin">Can. 6. the end. 13.</note> 
               <hi>When Iſrael ſhall be the third with Aegypt and Aſſyria, that is, in</hi> Africa <hi>and</hi> Aſia, <hi>even a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the midſt of the Land, whom the Lord of hoaſts ſhall bleſs, ſaying, bleſſed be Aegypt my people, and Aſſyria the work
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183677:5"/>of my hands, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>mine Inheritance.</hi> Seeing then it appears this will be the iſſue of the troubles now begun, and ſeeing our Saviour doth promiſe that for the <hi>Elects ſake the days of tribulation ſhall be ſhortned;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.22.</note> therefore we may conceive that it will not be long before they ſhall be reſtored, and with them the Nations be quieted; for this cauſe taking more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular notice of their preſent condition, to obſerve how Providence doth ſit them for their deliverance, and prepare a way to bring to paſs, we ſhall conſider, firſt, in what ſtate they are now at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where their deliverance will be wrought,<note place="margin">1.</note> and firſt begun, according to that of <hi>Mica</hi> 4 8. <hi>O Tower of the flock, the ſtrong hold of the daughter of Sion, unto thee ſhall it come, even the firſt dominion; the Kingdom ſhall come to the daughter of Jeruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.</note> Secondly, How the way is a preparing to bring their deliverance to paſs.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Their Diſtreſs.</head>
               <p>THE State of the <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of late was ſuch, that they could not live and ſubſiſt there, without ſome year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupply and contribution from their Brethren abroad, becauſe the place doth yield them little or no trading, whereby to maintain themſelves; but their love to the place doth oblige them to remain there, although with great poverty and want; And their Brethren abroad among the Nations, have been willing to uphold them there at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that the place ſhould not be left deſtitute of ſome conſiderable number of their Nation, to keep as it were poſſeſſion, or at leaſt a foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it, and to ſhew their hopes, till a full reſtitution come; Therefore the <hi>Jews</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> of <hi>Pruſſia</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> where great multitudes of that Nation were ſeated, were wont in former time to ſend to the <hi>German Jews,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> yearly about 30000 imperiall Dollars; which will amount, if we miſtake not, to 6563 pounds ſterling, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts yearly; by which means they ſubſiſted in ſome tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, and paid to the grand Signior of their taxes; but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183677:5"/>ſince the deſolation, brought by war upon <hi>Poland,</hi> and the other parts, whence that ſupply was ſent unto them, they have been in great extremity of want; inſomuch, that in the year one thouſand ſix hundred to death, and the taxes laid upon them by the Turks, being rigorouſly exacted, they were haled into priſon, their Synagogues were ſhut up, their Rabbi's and Elders beaten and cruelly uſed. So that to find relief, becauſe none came from <hi>Poland, Lithuania,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> by the late war, and none could be had in thoſe parts form their own, by reaſon of the general Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which the Turks without Mercy laid upon them all, they ſend two of their chief Rabbi's to their Brethren in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> to acquaint them with their ſtate, and to deſire ſome help from them. The chief of the Rabbi's was called <hi>Nathan Saphira,</hi> ſon to the high Lord, <hi>Ruben David Tavel,</hi> a man of great learning, and skill in their <hi>Cabala,</hi> and of a very pious, holy and humble diſpoſition, who comming with his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon this errand, and finding at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> little relief from the <hi>Portugal Jews,</hi> became accidentally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſome of our Chriſtian friends, who pittied their Condition, and were of their own accord moved to procure ſome relief unto them among their other Chriſtian friends; and the whole ſum which they then received from the Dutch Jews in <hi>Europe,</hi> amounted to ſix thouſand Ryx-dollars, which we conceive to be about one thouſand three hundred thirteen pounds, five ſhillings; and the Contributions which the Chriſtians in <hi>Holland</hi> gave them, amounted to three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ninety Ducats, which if we miſtake not, is one hundred ſeventy five pounds ten ſhillings. With this money they went away; and it availed them only to diſcharge the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of their capital debts, and to make ſome preſents to their great ones, that further time might be granted unto them, and the three hundred ninety Ducats relieved ſome of their private wants. This relief was made over unto them in the year one thouſand ſix hundred fifty ſix; and having received it, they have written a letter of Acknowledgment end Thanks, dated at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the 22 of April, 1657. wherein the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183677:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:183677:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:183677:7"/>Continuance of their lamentable condition is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to be this: that for the payment of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital debt, which in two years ſpace they have bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over unto the <hi>Baſſa,</hi> who rules over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged their Lives, Court, School, Wives and Children to him, and in the mean time they hunger and thirſt, and go from houſe to houſe for a bit of bread, unto their <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> Brethren that dwell at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who are in little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter caſe then theſe German Jews, becauſe the <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Portugals</hi> from abroad, help them with ſomething; nor durſt they go to any other to beg, beſides their own Nation, or their Proſelytes; which was a great aggravation of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, when their own either cannot, or will not aſſiſt them, as in the caſe of <hi>Rabbi Nathan Saphira</hi> it fell out; for the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal Jewes</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> not ſo aſſiſting him, becauſe they alledged that the <hi>Portugal</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Jews</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at <hi>Hebron</hi> and <hi>Zephit</hi> and other places in <hi>Judaea,</hi> did depend upon them, and were ſupplyed by them; yet nevertheleſs, having heard, that the Chriſtians had aſſiſted <hi>Rabbi Nathan</hi> and his Companion with a Contribution, and ſuſpecting that they had made their application to crave that aſſiſtance from the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, they were intending to have diſgraced him in their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, till they were otherwiſe informed, and having under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that the ſupply came not by any application of the Rabbi to the Chriſtians; but by the free offering of the Chriſtians to help him without his craving of it, which could not be taken ill, if the Rabbi only received what was freely offered, they did acquieſce: this is to be noted to ſhew the greatneſs of their ſtrait; when by the Principles of their Religion, they were bound up from ſeeking any relief, but only from their own people, although no relief could be had by any of them; ſo that they were obliged rather to ſtarve, then to crave help from ſtrangers, either Chriſtians, Mahumetans, or Heathens, when they were in want, although now of late they of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> have deſired relief of ſuch as pitty them, although they be Chriſtians. This was a hard caſe, and therefore required the greater Compaſſion; but yet the more hard, becauſe ſo few were inclined to have compaſſion upon them. From all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183677:7"/>which it is to be concluded, that as their Caſe is more hard then ordinary, ſo their deliverance muſt come by a way which is extraordinary: for all other Nations, when they are diſtreſſed by any enemy, they have ſome Neighbour people to flie to as friends, but theſe have none at all; therefore they muſt look up to God alone for their deliverance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> The preparing of a way for their Deliverance.</head>
               <p>BY their deliverance we underſtand, firſt, The enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their mind, to acknowledge the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. Secondly, Their freedom from the diſtreſs wherein they are by being kept out of the Land of their Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. And when ever God ſhall remove, either their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or their Captivity, their whole deliverance both ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and bodily will be wrought; becauſe the one will follow upon the other. Now we find ſome clear preparations begun to be ſet a foot for both theſe parts of their Deliverance.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Toward their bodily deliverance from their Captivity and Diſperſion. We conceive that the diſtreſs of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which is coming upon the whole face of the earth, is a manifeſt preparation; and that two ways: partly by driving them out from among the Nations, where they cannot abide any longer, and forcing them to draw cloſer together for their mutual relief: partly by awakening in them more earneſt deſires and thoughts of the Promiſe, that they ſhall return unto their own Inheritance: by which means, as ſoon as they ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>waters of the great River</hi> Euphrates <hi>dryed up,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 16.12. Eſa. 19.18, &amp;c.</note> they will be moved to reſolve upon a march unto their own land from all quarters, and in <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria</hi> is expected will be their Rendevouz in two bodies; as it is ſaid in <hi>Can.</hi> 6.13. You will ſee in the <hi>Shulamite</hi> at her return <hi>the company of two Armies.</hi> The diſtreſs then of the Nations driving them to theſe two places, is a preparative for their return.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:183677:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Another preparation of the way for their return, is that God doth ſtill appear for them in the Extremity of their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, when they can find no help from men; and that in this great Calamity, wherein they now are, there is yet a door of hope left open unto them; whereby Providence doth ſupport them in it, that they ſhould not utterly periſh; whence we muſt gather, that although God will have them to be <hi>caſt down;</hi> yet he will not ſuffer them to be deſtroyed; and although he will have them perplexed, yet he will not ſuffer them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, of which things there are clear Inſtances to be given, lately fallen out, which ought to be obſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Query </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, That God did appear for them in their utmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, when no help could be obtained, or expected from men: an inſtance hereof is this: that about the year 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. when there was for a long time no rain fallen upon <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the land about it, ſo that they were all in great extremity, both Jews and Turks, and like to periſh; the Turks having for a ſeaſon humbled themſelves, and prayed unto God after their manner for rain; and receiving no anſwer from heaven, they did conceive that God was angry with them, becauſe the Jews were ſuffered to live among them; therefore in great rage with drawn ſwords they went to the Jews, and threatned them, that if within three days they did not obtain Rain from heaven, they ſhould all be put to death. Whereupon the Jews having appointed a ſolem faſt, and the third day being allaſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at a place which they call the <hi>Sepulcher</hi> of <hi>Zachary,</hi> they prayed till noon, and after noon the clouds gathered, and with thunder they poured ſuch a flood of rain, that all the Ciſterns were filled and did run over: by which means they were ſaved from death, and it was made manifeſt that the Lord did own them, and accepted of their prayers, when none but he could help them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Another inſtance is in this their preſent Calamity; for when in the year one thouſane ſix hundred fifty five, they were in ſuch want, that four hundred of their widdows dyed by famine: and that they could expect no relief from any of their own Nations in <hi>Judea;</hi> &amp; having ſent into <hi>Europe</hi> to thoſe of their Nation, theſe alſo ſupplyed them no more but for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183677:8"/>the intereſt of their debt: ſo that all help from men ſeemed to fail them; it pleaſed God ſo to order it, that without any application of theirs unto Chriſtians, ſome pious and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſouls, were moved of their own accord to reflect upon their condition, and without their knowledge to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Collection for them, which did amount to ſome eaſe of their diſtreſs; although not to a total relief: and ſince that time God hath alſo moved the new Turkiſh <hi>Baſha</hi> to ſhew ſome kindneſs unto them; for after his arrival at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> he ſatisfied all their Creditors with his own goods and wares, and made an agreement with the Jews, favorably uſing them; that in ſtead of fifteen thouſand Ryx-dollars, they ſhould pay him only ſeven thouſand, and that on two years term without any intereſt. Yet with this hard Condition, that if the agreement was not then performed, they muſt all become his ſlaves, and that he ſhould do with them what he would: So that it is apparent, that although the Lord ſuffers them to come to great, and (in all humane appearance) invincible ſtraits, yet he doth not ſuffer them to be ſwallowed up by the ſame, but ſheweth ſtill ſome iſſue; ſo that there is a door of hope yet open for them to eſcape; which in the language of Providence doth ſignifie thus much, That the Lord doth not utterly caſt them off, but hath ſtill Mercy in ſtore for them, till they be fitted for a full deliverance: for all theſe tryals in the way of Providence and Mercy, tend to nothing elſe but to bring them to a ſenſe of their ſins, that they may be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the ſame by repentance, and brought to the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, to receive by faith the pardon thereof for his ſake; whereunto we Chriſtians ſhould ſet our ſelves to become inſtrumental towards them; for now being thus hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and finding our love and compaſſion not ſhut up againſt them in their miſery, their ear may be open to us to hearken without prejudice unto the Truth of our Faith and Hope.</p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" rend="hr"/>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:183677:9"/>
               <p>BUT beſides all theſe Tokens of Favour, whereof we have particular Aſſurance, which we look upon as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt preparatives for their reſtitution, there is one thing more to be mentioned, whereunto we may give ſo much credit as is due to a vulgar rumor, and that is this. That whereas the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> heretofore was exceeding barren, and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull then any of the other neighbour Countries; it is now reported to be become within the ſpace of five or ſix years exceeding fruitfull, yielding ten times the encreaſe of that which formerly it did yield: and if this report be true which we cannot certainly affirm, but only give it as a report, come from ſome of the Inhabitants: then we may make this certain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture upon it, that God is not only fitting them to return unto their own Land by the forenamed Tryals, but he is fitting alſo their land to receive them: for even as for the ſins of a people God turns the fruitfull land into barrenneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.34. So when he is reconciled unto a people, he doth promiſe that he will cauſe the Heavens and the earth, and the fruits of the ground to anſwer the deſires of his people, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.21, 22. And if now this begins to fall out in the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> after ſo long a Barrenneſs, we may truly conceive, that he is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it for more Inhabitants then formerly it could entertain; and that he is about to make good the Propheſie of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32.43. <hi>Rejoyce ye Nations with his Perple, for he will avenge the blood of his ſervants, and will render vengeance to his Adverſaries, and will be mercifull to his land and to his people:</hi> and that as he brought not <hi>Adam</hi> into the world, till all the creatures were fitted for his entertainment; ſo he will not bring his people into their land, till it be fitted to give them a livelyhood, when they ſhall return unto it.</p>
               <p>Theſe Acts of Providence towards them in reſpect of their whole Nation,<note place="margin">Mic. 4.8. Rom. 11.8.</note> and more eſpecially in reſpect of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which <hi>is the Tower of the flock, and the ſtrong hold of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Sion,</hi> we look upon as preparatives only at a diſtance to give a general proſpect a far off, concerning Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:183677:9"/>to ſhew that they are not utterly caſt away out of his Remembrance; but that having ſtill a deſign to do them good, for their Fathers ſake, he will fit them thereby for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deliverance from their ignorance and ſpiritual Captivity; concerning the removal of which, we find alſo ſome remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable preparatives wrought among them: becauſe it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent by ſome paſſages of the converſe of ſome of our friends with their chief <hi>Rabbi Nathan Saphira,</hi> that the ſenſe which their more underſtanding Rabbi's have of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> is not ſo far diſtant from the Principles of Chriſtianity as we ordinarily have imagined, and that the frame of their Spirits, at this time is made more ſuſceptible of the Truth of the Goſpel, then at any time heretofore. And to make out this we ſhall inſert ſome Extracts out of a friends letter to <hi>J.D.</hi> dated in April one thouſand ſix hundred fifty ſeven, whereby the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certiy of <hi>Rabbi Nathan,</hi> and his underſtanding in holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries will be evidenced. Mr. <hi>P. Serrarius</hi> then writes thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHen on a certain time we were ſpeaking together concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi> Meſſiah, <hi>and I was alledging the Hiſtory of the Patriarck</hi> Joſeph, <hi>how he was ſold by his brethren, and the reſt of that Hiſtorie, till he was manifeſted unto them, when as they imagine nothing leſs then that he was alive, one of the Jews at</hi> Amſterdam <hi>who ſtood by, ſaid inſtantly,</hi> I know what you mean, as if you would make us believe, that your Chriſt were yet alive. But <hi>Rabbi Nathan</hi> reproving his raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſaid to him, Do not ſay ſo, Let come whoever will come, our prayers and wiſhes are to this effect ſimply, That God would be pleaſed to reveal him. <hi>Whereunto when we had repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Except Chriſt reveal himſelf, we deſire not that you ſhould believe us: but if he as another</hi> Joſeph, <hi>who is long ago ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be dead, ſhould again ſhew himſelf alive unto you; ſurely you would no leſs then your Fore-fathers, believe your own eyes: they both gave their aſſent hereunto. Then it was asked of</hi> Nathan, <hi>what he underſtood by the place of</hi> Iſaiah 53.4, 5. <hi>He hath born our griefs and carried our ſorrows, and he was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183677:10"/>wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities, the chaſtiſment of our Peace was upon him; and with his ſtripes we are healed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Queſtion was of whom the prophet did ſpeak there; He anſwered plainly, That he ſpoke of the</hi> Meſſiah; <hi>and when we did wonder at the Anſwer, and had replied, that commonly that place of Scripture was otherwiſe underſtood by the Jews:</hi> He ſaid, That by the <hi>Cabala</hi> it was moſt evident, that the place could not be underſtood of any other; and to prove this, he did alledge the words of the foregoing Chapter, 52.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Behold ny ſervant ſhall deal prudently, he ſhall be exalted, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled, and be very high, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; in which word he ſaid, That the undoubted tokens of this Myſterie was contained; for by the letter <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> was meant <hi>Moſes,</hi> by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Adam,</hi> and by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>David:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theſe Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſtical Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s they are no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>round of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nterpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yet if to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>em they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ring forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ue Goſpel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oncluſions, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e have no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>auſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt their uſing of them.</note> and that of this ſervant of God three things were fore-told and declared, which have all the ſame meaning and might have been expreſſed by one word of exaltation, if the holy Ghoſt had not had a reſpect to theſe three members of the Compariſon; namely, That this ſervant of God was to be exalted above <hi>Moſes,</hi> extolled above <hi>Adam,</hi> and made higher then <hi>David.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Above <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe he will give a Law, which ſhall be exalted above the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Above <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe he ſhall be Head of a Creation which ſhall be extolled above that which was in <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Above <hi>David,</hi> becauſe he ſhall be a King higher and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier then <hi>David.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And of none can theſe things be ſaid, but only of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah;</hi> whence he did conclude, that the following words of ch. 52. and 53. muſt be underſtood only of the <hi>Meſſiah. When then we inquired how he would interpret the foregoing words of the</hi> 53. <hi>chap.</hi> concering the <hi>Meſſiah:</hi> He anſwered that the Spirit of the Meſſiah had a being before <hi>Adam;</hi> and as ſoon as <hi>Adam</hi> fell under the Condemnation of Death and curſe, he was moved with a moſt inward Compaſſion, and coming down from Heaven, he took the whole weight of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which neither <hi>Adam</hi> nor the whole generation of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:183677:10"/>mankind could have born upon himſelfe, which he ſtill bears; that unto miſerable mankind time and ſpace may be given to repent and be reconciled with God, that if he make good uſe thereof he may be freed from Condemnation, and be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted again to Gods favour: but if not, it will come to paſs, that the Meſsiah will withdraw his ſhoulders from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Burden, and leave to every impenitent and obſtinate ſinner his own burden to bear it for himſelf; and in the mean time, whiles this time of Repentance and Reconciliation laſts, he it is who ſince the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> hath born our ſickneſſes, and carried our ſorrows, who for our tranſgreſsions and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities was bruiſed, and upon whom the chaſtiſment of our Peace was laid; which if the Spirit of the Meſſiah had not been pleaſed to do, the ſickneſſes and pains of our ſins had long ago conſumed us; our tranſgreſſions and iniquities would have bruiſed us, and no hope of Peace or Salvation would ever have appeared unto us.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen I heard theſe things, my bowels were inwardly ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within me, and it ſeemed to me, that I did not hear a Jew, but a Chriſtian, and a Chriſtian of no mean underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who did reliſh the things of the Spirit, and was admitted to the inward myſteries of our Religion. Another time when we were together at a meeting with ſomn friends pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, where we uſe to read ſome parcell of the Scripture, he came unexpected among us, and we thought good to read Chriſts Sermon upon the Mount, in</hi> Matthew 5.6, 7. <hi>And while we did read the Dutch</hi> tranſlation, <hi>we gave him the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew tranſlation of</hi> Munſter <hi>to look into, telling him that this was the Law of our Chriſt, that he ſhould read it, and then let us know what he did judge thereof: this he did, and when he had read all, with a great deal of ingenuity, he made an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment</hi> that therein the ground and fountain of all Wiſdom was contained, and that whoſoever ſhould keep thoſe Commandments would be more juſt then he, or hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> people, and he took notice of ſome things which he the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:183677:11"/>were taken out of the moſt pure and antient <hi>Rabbins; and when at that meeting we had, not without Tears, and much devour Contrition of mind, made prayers for the Jews as well as for our ſelves, that God would blot out our ſins and theirs, and remember his Mercy, and reſtore the holy Spirit which they had loſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Theſe things ſeemed very much to move him, and he made no doubt to affirm openly,</hi> that if there were but ten men at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who ſhould thus with out heart pray for the coming of the Meſſiah, that without all doubt he would ſuddenly come; <hi>And being asked, how he did underſtand the place of</hi> Malachy 3.1. <hi>Behold I will ſend my Meſſenger, and he ſhall prepare the way for me, and the Lord whom ye ſeek ſhall ſuddenly come to his Temple, &amp;c.</hi> He ſaid by the Meſſenger <hi>Elias</hi> was meant, and by the Lord was meant the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> who ſhould come and ſhew himſelf to be ſeen at the Temple, not of ours, that is, of mans building, but in his own Temple, which he hath built in the heavens, and which he will let down from Heaven to the earth: and when I asked him, <hi>Whether the Jews alone were to be admitted into that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</hi> He anſwered No; but that his Temple was ordained for all the people of the Gentiles, who ever ſhall fear God in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity. <hi>And once when we were ſpeaking of the Promiſes made unto</hi> Abraham;<note place="margin">Gen. 15.19, 20.</note> He obſerved that God promiſed to caſt out ten Nations out of the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> for his ſake, and would give their poſſeſsions to his Poſterity, but that ſince the days of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> no more but ſeven Nations have been caſt out, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Hittites,</hi> the <hi>Perizzites,</hi> the <hi>Rephaims,</hi> the <hi>Amorites,</hi> the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> the <hi>Gergaſites</hi> and the <hi>Jebuſites:</hi> the theee firſt, viz. The <hi>Kenites,</hi> the <hi>Keneſites</hi> and the <hi>Kedmonites</hi> are reſerved for the times of the Meſsiah; which he would have to anſwer the ten <hi>Sephiroth,</hi> whereof the ſeven laſt are called by the Cabaliſts ſimply, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is, Palaces; but the three firſt taken together as one are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is, the Temple of the Holy of Holies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whence I by my ſelf drew this clear Argument for the Reign of Chriſt on earth. If the Promiſe made to</hi> Abraham <hi>concerning the Land of</hi> Canaan <hi>it not yet fulfilled, then it muſt be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183677:11"/>But it is evident that it is not yet fulfilled. Firſt; theſe three former Nations were never yet ſubdued. Secondly. Becauſe the three Nations yet to be ſubdued will conſtitute the Temple which ſhall be called the holy of holies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the ſubduing of the ſeven which</hi> Joſhuah <hi>conquered, did only conſtitute ſome Palaces or courts, which might be polluted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed were polluted, overthrown and trodden under ſoot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When at a time he did ſup with us, and ſaw us praying with our hands joined and lifted up unto Heaven; he asked us why we did pray with that geſture: It was anſwered, that it was of old the cuſtom ſo to pray, derived from</hi> Moſes, <hi>who in the mount prayed againſt</hi> Amaleck <hi>with his hands lifted up unto heaven; whereunto the Rabbi ſaid,</hi> No doubt whoſoever can lift up pure hands with <hi>Moſes</hi> unto heaven, he will be heard of God as <hi>Moſes</hi> was; but it is to be underſtood, that then both hands are purely lifted up unto heaven, and the ten fingers erected on high, when one directly is ſettled towards God, with the whole ſtrength of his ſoul, and hath a good conſcience toward Gods ten Commandments, and that the purity and ſincerity of the whole man doth require, that every one ſhould be inwardly ſo compoſed, as his body is outwardly conſtitued; therefore ſeeing they of his Nation were not conſcious to themſelves of ſuch a frame of ſpirit, they durſt not lift up both their hands unto heaven, but they keep them in their boſom, taking hold of the left hand by the right, becauſe the right hand doth ſignifie Mercy, and the left Gods Juſtice; and by that geſture they petition: that God by his Mercy would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain his Juſtice, that it may not break out upon them miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinners to conſume them, but would firſt prepare and form them unto all that is good. I could relate many other things of this kind, which ſhew a truly devout and humble mind: one thing I ſhall yet add; When it was askt of him, Whether he was not afraid of his life, chiefly he being a Jew, a people above all other Nations hated of all, through which he was to go? he did anſwer, If I look upon my ſelf, I ſee my ſelf altogether unworthy of any mercy at Gods hands, or that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:183677:12"/>he ſhould admit of my prayers;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſpeaks here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e a legal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>w, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10, 2, 3.</note> but that which gives me ſome Confidence of life, are the calamities and extream Straits of the poor at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the merits of the Fore-fathers, and their Faith in God. I believe that their prayers will be of weight towards the Father of the needy. <hi>Here you may ſee in a Spirit of Humility Faith, and in faith an humble and ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying Spirit. What do you think? Is it to be believed that Chriſt is far diſtant from a ſoul thus conſtituted? or that any ſuch thing can be formed without Chriſt in a man? for my own part, I confeſs I think I ſee Chriſt in his Spirit; and I cannot but love him, and thoſe that are like him, of which he ſaith many are at</hi> Jeruſalem: <hi>for I eſteem them the true brethren of him, that is, our</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and their</hi> Joſeph, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>Thus far <hi>Peter Serearius.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:183677:12"/>
               <p>FRom whence we may gather this Concluſion, that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, the Lord by humbling their Spirits, and moving them to look up unto him for the accompliſhment of his Promiſes, and letting them ſee, that the Myſteries of divine Wiſdom, and the way of Righteouſneſs are revealed more clearly to us by Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> in the Goſpel, then ever they were to them by their Rabbi's, and that there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtency, but rather a Conſonancy with the Promiſe, that Jeſus ſhall be revealed to them as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was once to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and by bringing the chief of them to be acquainted with ſuch Chriſtians as freely love them for Chriſts ſake, and willingly help them in their ſtraits, and give them cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Truth of the Goſpel without prejudice; I ſay from all theſe Circumſtances we may gather this Concluſion, that the Lord doth prepare a way for them to be converted unto Chriſtianity; which is yet more evident by ſome other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, wherewith ſome of us are acquainted. Namely, that ſome of thoſe afflicted Jews at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> begin now to confeſs, <hi>That their Fore-fathers did wickedly in putting</hi> Jeſus <hi>of</hi> Nazareth <hi>to death, and that he was a juſt man, and that the Spirit of the Meſſiah was in him, and that for putting him and others to death, they ought to repent, ſeeing they cannot attribute this great wrath which is gone forth againſt them to any other cauſe ſo remarkable as to this ſin.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☜</note> Now if theſe Confeſſions begin to be made among ſome of the chief of them, as ſome of us know that they are; it is a clear token, that God is preparing and fitting them for Mercy by the acknowledgement of their ſin, and repentance for putting Chriſt to death: and if once their hearts begin to be moved with remorſe for this ſin, no doubt they will obtain pardon. We are alſo certainly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that the New Teſtament in Hebrew of the tranſlation of <hi>Munſter,</hi> being far different from the Hebrew phraſe, which is uſed in Scripture, is taken along to be brought to <hi>Judea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☜</note> that it may be put in Scripture phraſe, and ſo ſent back again to <hi>Amſterdam</hi> to be printed; and if once they begin to read
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183677:13"/>the new Teſtament; as a true Hiſtory in their own Hebrew Dialect, there can be no greater preparation for their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion then this will be; and we know that God is now ſetting this very thing a foot among them. Whence we may conclude that he is fitting them for Mercy by the means of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching to the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt; and nothing will approach them ſo effectually to that knowledge, next unto the Spirit of Grace and Supplication to be poured out upon them, as firſt, The Communication of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their Tongue by ſome of their own Rabbi's unto them. 2. as the Unity of Chriſtians holding forth unto them with one conſent the main ſubſtance of Chriſtianity, which brings Salvation unto all. And 3. as the opening unto them the Bowels of our Charity in theſe opportunities of their diſtreſs and perplexty, that they may find ſome relief by theſe three means: All which God is now ſetting a work toward them: the work may be carried on with ſucceſs, till the Lord come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>his</hi> Temple. In expectation whereof, all whoſe hearts are touched with compaſſion to them in their bleeding condition, and have longing deſires for their deliverance, are exhorted to teſtifie the ſame by their prayers, and by the opening of their heart and hand liberally towards them. And how bleſſed ſhall they be that ſhall have a hand in helping to make <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> a Glory in the whole Earth!</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:183677:13"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 122.6.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>PRay for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they ſhall proſper that love thee.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 41.1, 2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Bleſſed is he that conſidereth the poor; the Lord will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him in the time of trouble; the Lord will preſerve him and keep him alive, and he ſhall be bleſſed upon the Earth, and thou wilt not deliver him unto the will of his Enemies.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2 Cor. 8.9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>You know the Grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that though he was rich, yet for your ſakes he became poor, that ye through his poverty might be rich.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2 Cor. 9.6, 7.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>He which ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly: and he which ſoweth bountifully ſhall reap bountifully: Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man as be purpoſeth in his heart, not grudingly, or of neceſsity: for God loveth a cheerfull Giver.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:183677:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183677:14"/>
            <head>An <hi>Appendix</hi> to the foregoing Information received from Beyond-Seas ſince it was Printed; to be added in the former pages, that are there ſhewed in the Margen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſtate of the Jews at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> hath been many hundred years of late ſuch,<note place="margin">To pag. 4. l. 17.</note> as that they ever lived of the ſupply and Contributions from their brethren abroad: becauſe the place doth yield but little occaſion for them to maintain themſelves: and beſides thoſe that betake themſelves thither, are either Old men or Women, only to do penitency and lay down their bones near the Sepulchers of their fore-fathers: or of younger men that for reſpect to the holineſs of the place (as ſuppoſing God to be nearer there, and that all prayers muſt needs aſcend that way into heaven) come thither, there to ply devotion and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency for the ſins of themſelves and the whole Nation: and therefore cannot attend any trading, but all their time is taken up with praying, reading and hearing Sermons; as alſo with faſtings and watchings and the like penitential Exerciſes: which intent and endeavours their Brethren abroad amongſt the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons well knowing, and with all deſiring to keep (as it were) poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, or at leaſt a footing in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to ſhew their
<pb facs="tcp:183677:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>holineſs till a full reſtitution come, have been ever willing to uphold them in it: and to that purpoſe, wherever any Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues of Jews are, on every Sabbath-day a Collection is made for the poor at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and what ſo is gathered, they are to ſend thither every year. Therefore the Jews of <hi>Poland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Turks (and eſpecially their debts made for want of ſupply amongſt the Citizens) being rigorouſly exacted,<note place="margin">Pag. 5. l. 6.</note> they were haled into priſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Inſtance hereof is this,<note place="margin">Pa. 8. l. 14.</note> that in the year 5399. from the Creation, which is now nineteen years ago, there was a great drought in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which had put all Inhabitants to prayers, the Neceſſity being extream: but the worſt of all was this, that an apoſtated Jew going out to the Turks, perſwaded unto the then <hi>Baſſa,</hi> the Lord <hi>Mahomet Baſſa,</hi> that the ſole cauſe that the heaven were ſhut up, were the Jews by reaſon of their diſobedience unto God; whereupon an Edict was put forth, commanding all Jews, great and ſmall, young and old, to be caſt out of the Town preſently. Whereupon ſome eight of their Eldeſt were ſent up to the ſaid <hi>Baſſa:</hi> which Eldeſt with great Expences beſtowed partly on the <hi>Baſſa,</hi> and partly on his Conſellours, had much to do, to crave only three dayes delay: If perhaps within that time the Lord ſhould accept of their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and penitency: If not, and that the Lord gave no Rain, he might do with him what he pleaſed. This being ſo ſtated, it was proclaimed throughout the City, that if within three dayes no rain came, all the Jews ſhould be expelled, and their goods made prize to the Turks: and whoſoever ſhould be found re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, was to be killed. Hence aroſe a dolefull lamentation amongſt the Jews: a continual faſting for thoſe three nights and dayes was put upon all, except Babes and Women with Child or in Child-bed, who were bound only to one day and night: So they prayed and humbled themſelves all that while with great Cries and Weepings, ſo that the voyce of it was heard throughout the City; and on the Evening on the ſecond day, they ſeeing no likely-hood their prayers ſhould be heard, and judging their ſins to be too great, they took a Reſolution, like to <hi>Saul,</hi> rather to kill one another, one Brother the other, the Father his Children, the Husband his Wife, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then to ſuffer themſelves to be polluted by the mercileſs Turks. Yet
<pb facs="tcp:183677:15"/>one thing they would firſt requeſt of the <hi>Baſſa. viz.</hi> That they might all go out to the Sepulchre of the Prophet <hi>Zachary,</hi> which was out of the Town, and whither they could not come without his conſent. So one <hi>R. Emanuel Alba-chry</hi> was ſent unto him, who hearing of their deſperate Reſolutions pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed them and ſaid, Go ye and make your prayers there, if perhaps God might hear you and ſave you from being kild. So on the morning of the third day early, all went forth and laid themſelves down at the Sepulchre of <hi>Zachary,</hi> and there wept bitterly. One <hi>R. Aſaria</hi> made a very pathetical Sermon, and cauſed all the people to weep, and ſo did <hi>R. Meyer</hi> likewiſe. And at Length aroſe one <hi>R. Samuel,</hi> who put the people in mind of the ſins of their fore-fathers, and againſt this Prophet, at whoſe Tomb they now were proſtrated, how they aroſe againſt him, and ſtoned him moſt cruelly: how (ſaid he,) ſhall we here obtain mercy at his feet, ſeeing oury Fathers had no mercy on him? At which words the people wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, and ſtrook their hands together,<note place="margin">2 Chren. 21.24. Mat. 23.35 <hi>with</hi> Zach. 1.1.</note> and poured out tears as water, and lift up their voyces, men and women, young and old: and the Lord remembred<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe are the words of <hi>R. Samuel Ben Seth,</hi> as the next page ſhew</note> his ſurety: and he made this <hi>R. Samuel</hi> to think on the words of the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> on the Mount <hi>Carmel,</hi> when he ſaid to his man go up and ſee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore commanded the people to Go ſeven times round about the Sepulchre, at the firſt Circuition he ordained <hi>Pſalm</hi> 24. and certain prayers to be pronounced; at the ſecond he aſſigned <hi>Pſalm</hi> 48. and other prayers, and ſo at each of the ſeven Circuits ſome peculiar Pſalm and prayer till the Veſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time came. And then the people going forth ſaw a little Cloud on the Weſt ſide of Heaven as large as the palm of a hand. That very day it had been very hot, even as it had been Mid Sommer, ſo that no man could have believed any rain could have faln that day; which made that the Turks had already gathered up ſtones, wherewith they thought to have ſtone the Jews at their return into the City: But ſuch was Gods providence that even that day before Sun-ſetting the ſaid Cloud grew thick, and a wind began to blow, and then came Thundring, and Lightning, and ſuch a bleſſed ſhown of Rain, that in two or three hours all the Ciſterns were brim-full; ſo that for the Rains ſake the Jews were forced to remain that whole Night in Holes and Concavities
<pb facs="tcp:183677:16"/>of the Sepulchre. And when on the next morning the Women went firſt of all toward <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Turkiſh Women met them by the way, and Congratulated them, that God had heard their prayers; and ſo likewiſe many of the Chief Turks met with the men, and brought them ſome preſents of fruits and Confitures; and the <hi>Baſſa</hi> beſtowed a ſuite of apparrell on every one of their Rabbies.</p>
            <p>This is an extract drawn out of an Authentique Copie, written by the ſaid <hi>R. Samuel,</hi> and ſigned by all the Elders of the High-Dutch Synagoge at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> 1657. <hi>April.</hi> 22. An other Inſtance of the ſame kind we could add of the year (as we count) 1651. and another yet ſince while <hi>Rab. Nathan</hi> was here; but this afore mentioned being moſt Conſiderable and moſt Authentical, and exactly pend, whereas the others are but received by word of mouth, we ſhall here deſiſt. This being ſufficient to manifeſt unto us, that however deſpiſed this people is by men, yet that the Lord doth yet own them and accept of their payers, when none but he can help, when ever with a penitent and contrite heart they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of their ſins and call for mercy, as we have ſeen here at the Sepulchre of the Prophet <hi>Zachary.</hi> Would to God they agreed once to go out high-wayes to the Sepulchre of Chriſt, which is as much certain there as that of <hi>Zachary;</hi> and who knows to what purpoſe; and that there they recalled to mind alſo how their Fore-fathers dealt with Jeſus.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ac. 12.10.</note> O what a mourning would follow! and what a ſhour of ſoul quickning Rain! what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulation of all creatures, what a joy in Heaven and earth!</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
